Cadwell Family Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Cadwell family correspondence
1834-1905
1870-1893
WA MSS S-2933
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
Letters to Louie Earl Williams of Buckeye, California, and Reno, Nevada, chiefly from her sister and brother-in-law, Julia Earl Cadwell and Edwin Cadwell, that discuss farm and social life in Crawford County, Iowa, 1870-1893. The collection also includes letters by other family members and friends, including Jennie Ann Huckstep and Ella Jefferson. Many letters are addressed to her parents, Asa Colton Earl and Nancy Weakley Allred Earl. A few letters are written to her husband, William J. Williams. The collection also includes fragmentary business records related to Asa Colton Earl, 1834-1855, and two photographs, 1901-circa 1905.
Cadwell family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Vinson on the Henry R. Wagner Fund. 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Julia Earl Cadwell (1838-1880)
Julia Earl Cadwell was the daughter of Asa Colton Earl (1810-1891) and Minerva Rich Earl (1816-1840), members of the Mormon Church; her mother was a sister of Charles Coulson Rich (1809-1883), an early leader in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Her siblings were Joseph Rich Earl (1836-1898) and Nancy Minerva Earl Leavitt (1840-1911).
In 1843, Asa Colton Earl married Nancy Weakley Allred Earl (1815-1904) in Nauvoo, Illinois. They had seven children: Isaac W. Earl (1844-1864), Mary J. Earl (1846-1848), Artemesia Earl (1848-1934), Asa C. Earl (1850-1863), John A. Earl (1851-1910), Joel Earl (1853-1861), Louie Earl Williams (1855-1938). In 1860, the family lived in Union Township, Crawford County, Iowa. In 1870, the family lived in Buckeye, Yolo County, California.
Around 1860, Julia married Edwin Cadwell (born 1834), a farmer in Milford Township, Crawford County, Iowa. After her death, he married his cousin Jennie Murray Cadwell (born circa 1862) in 1881.
Biographical / Historical
Louie Earl Williams was the daughter of Asa Colton Earl and Nancy Weakley Allred Earl. In 1879, Louie married William J. Williams (1842-1924) in Reno, Nevada, where they operated a farm. They had four children: Jessie Julia Williams (1880-1888), William Ray Williams (born 1884), Roy Earl Williams (1886-1940) and Robin Leslie Williams (1889-1915).
Scope and Contents
Letters to Louie Earl Williams of Buckeye, California, and Reno, Nevada, chiefly from her sister and brother-in-law, Julia Earl Cadwell and Edwin Cadwell, that discuss farm and social life in Crawford County, Iowa, 1870-1893. The collection also includes letters by other family members and friends, including Jennie Ann Huckstep and Ella Jefferson. Many letters are addressed to her parents, Asa Colton Earl and Nancy Weakley Allred Earl. A few letters are written to her husband, William J. Williams. The collection also includes fragmentary business records related to Asa Colton Earl, 1834-1855, and two photographs, 1901-circa 1905.
Many letters written by Julia Earl Cadwell discuss her Christian faith and deteriorating health. A group of letters by Edwin Cadwell describe his wife's death from a uterine inflammation in September 1880, as well as his subsequent mourning and marriage the following year.
Arrangement
Arranged chronogically.
Mormons -- Iowa; Mormons -- California; Women -- West (U.S.) -- Correspondence; Crawford County (Iowa) -- Description and travel; Reno (Nev.) -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Cadwell family; Cadwell, Edwin, 1834-; Cadwell, Jennie Murray, approximately 1862-; Cadwell, Julia Earl, 1838-1880; Earl, Asa Colton, 1810-1891; Earl, Nancy Weakley Allred, 1815-1904; Huckstep, Jennie Ann, 1854-1885; Jefferson, Ella; Williams, Louie Earl, 1855-1938; Williams, William J., 1842-1924
- Letters to Louie Earl Williams and Papers, 1834-circa 1905; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Except where noted, this collection consists of letters to Louie Earl Williams.
  - Lindley, Oliver, receipt to Asa Colton Earl, 1834 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Promissary note with a clipped signature, probably Asa Colton Earl to Stutsman & Donnel, Council Bluffs, Iowa, 1854 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Stutsman & Donnel was a general store in Council Bluffs, Iowa.
  - Harrison County, Iowa, receipt to Asa Colton Earl for taxes, 1855 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cadwell, Edwin and Cadwell, Julia, Boyer River, Iowa, 1870 November 27-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, and Cadwell, Julia, Strawberry Point, Iowa, 1871 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Pleasant View, Iowa, 1872 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Deloit, Iowa, 1872 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Deloit, Iowa, 1872 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Deloit, Iowa, 1872 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cadwell, Edwin and Julia Cadwell, Deloit, Iowa, 1873 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1874 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1874 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Deloit, Iowa, 1875 May 2-3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1876 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Deloit, Iowa, 1877 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1877 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Huckstep, Jennie A., Alexander Morgan Co., Illinois, 1877 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jefferson, Ella, Woodbine, Iowa, 1877 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jefferson, Ella, Woodbine, Iowa, 1877 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Pleasant View, Iowa, 1877 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1878 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Williams, John. W., to William J. Williams, Elizabeth, Illinois, 1878 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Biographical/Historical note
    John W. Williams (1857-1929) was a brother of William J. Williams.
  - Huckstep, Jennie, Deloit, Iowa, 1878 May 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Deloit, Iowa, 1879 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Huckstep, Jennie, Vail, Iowa, 1879 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jefferson, Ella, Woodbine, Iowa, 1879 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1879 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Huckstep, Jennie, Vail, Iowa, 1879 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Enclosures include a swatch of cloth and pressed flowers.
  - Jefferson, Ella, Woodbine, Iowa, 1879 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Jefferson, Ella, Woodbine, Iowa, 1879 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cadwell, Louie E., Vail, Iowa, 1879 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Pleasant View, Iowa, 1879 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cadwell, Julia, and Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1880 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cadwell, Edwin,, Vail, Iowa, 1880 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, and Cadwell, Julia,, Vail, Iowa, 1880 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1880 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1880 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1880 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Iowa City, Iowa, 1880 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Jacksonville, Iowa, 1881 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1881 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1881 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1881 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, and Jennie Murray Cadwell, Vail, Iowa, 1881 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Cadwell, Jennie Murray, Vail, Iowa, 1881 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1882 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1882 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1883 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Jefferson, Ella,, Woodbine, Iowa, 1884 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1888 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Wright, Minerva Elizabeth Earl, Nonpareil, Box Butte County, Nebraska, 1888 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Minerva Elizabeth Earl Wright (1867-1915) was a daughter of Joseph C. Earl.
  - Cadwell, Edwin, Vail, Iowa, 1888 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Williams, Mary, Elizabeth, Illinois, 1888 August 8? (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Mary Ann Belk Williams (1861-1933) was the wife of George Douglas Williams (1852-1928), a brother of William J. Williams.
  - Williams, Isaac, and Theresa Reynolds Williams, Jo Daviess County, Illinois, 1889 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Isaac Williams (1816-1904) and Theresa Reynolds Williams (1821-1892) were the parents of William J. Williams.
  - Wright, Minerva, Alliance, Nebraska, 1893 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Unidentified photographer, Exterior portrait of a woman and man in front of a wooden house, probably Louie Earl Williams and William J. Williams in front of their home in Reno, Nevada, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Inscription on verso: The old house in 1901, and mother and father.
  - Issott, James H., San Jose, California, Studio portrait of Cynthia Louise Sheperd and her grandmother, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Cadwell, Julia, Iowa, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)